♪Confessing to the moon in the rustling wind back then♪
♪จันทร์เคยแจ่มกระจ่าง♪
♪Like a boat being swallowed up among the cities♪
♪พลันแปรเป็นทะเลคลั่ง♪
♪Watching the flowers fall in unease, worries and troubles fill my mind♪
♪ตระหนกฟังเสียงบุปผาโรย♪
♪Am I going to where I want♪
♪ทุกที่ที่ไป♪
♪To stay or to leave, you decide♪
♪ด้วยการไปหรืออยู่ของเจ้า♪
♪Nations are different♪
♪ปฐพีกับแผ่นดินก็ต่างกัน♪
♪One without desire is one that is not alive♪
♪ฟ้าดินไร้ใจ♪
♪Looking at the sky side by side♪
♪ร่วมเคียงชมนภา♪
♪We've gotten closer with time♪
♪กาลเข้มข้นกว่าเวลา♪
♪One glance, the city of Chang'an is bare♪
♪มองผ่านปราดเดียว♪
♪Among the ridiculous people and things is me♪
♪ในเรื่องราวเหลวไหลของผู้คน♪
=Episode 31=
=ตอนที่ 31=
Secondly,
ข้อสอง
you must take good care
เจ้าต้องดูแล
of your other siblings.
เหล่าพี่น้องคนอื่น ๆ ให้ดี
Promise me this.
เจ้าต้องสาบาน
Look at me.
มองหน้าพี่
No matter what happens in the future,
ไม่ว่าเกิดเรื่องอะไรขึ้น
no matter how difficult the situation is,
ไม่ว่าจะลำบากกว่านี้เพียงไร
you need to live on.
จงมีชีวิตต่อไป
You and your siblings must live on.
นำเหล่าพี่น้องมีชีวิตต่อไป
As long as you guys are still alive,
ขอเพียงพวกเจ้ายังมีชีวิตอยู่
as long as the descendants of the Qi Family are alive,
ลูกหลานตระกูลฉีมีชีวิตอยู่
the lineage of the Qi Family
เช่นนี้สายเลือดตระกูลฉี
will always be around.
ก็จะคงอยู่ตลอดกาล
Understood.
พ่ะย่ะค่ะ
I...
กระหม่อม
I think I can do so.
กระหม่อมน่าจะทำได้
Good.
เยี่ยม
Good boy.
น้องชายที่ดี
Brother?
เสด็จพี่
I...
ยังมี
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
What about
ยังมี ยังมี
the third question?
ยังมีคำถามข้อที่สามพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Your Majesty?
ฝ่าบาท
That is all I will ask.
ไม่มีแล้ว
As for the rest, you should act as you deem fit.
เจ้าก็ทำหน้าที่ให้ดีเถอะ
Brother,
เสด็จพี่
how is your body?
สุขภาพพระองค์เป็นอย่างไรบ้าง
They said they weren't able to cure your illness.
พวกเขาบอกว่าโรคของพระองค์รักษาไม่ได้แล้ว
I will
ข้า
hold on until the day you ascend the throne.
ต้องอดทนจนเจ้าขึ้นครองราชย์แน่
Qi Rong, you don't need to worry about that.
เจ้าวางใจเถอะ เจ้าแปด
Brother, please take care.
เสด็จพี่ทรงรักษาพระวรกายด้วย
The Chess Overseer has ordered me to send you two back to the palace.
ผู้นำสำนักหมากรุกให้กระหม่อม ส่งพวกพระองค์กลับวังพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
I am fine.
ข้าไม่เป็นไร
you insisted on seeing Prince An.
พระองค์ทรงยืนกรานจะเสด็จมาพบท่านอ๋องอัน
Actually, I knew you did it
ความจริงจุดประสงค์โดยแท้คือ
because you wanted to ask him about the third question, right?
ต้องการถามคำถามข้อที่สามกระมัง
The third question?
ข้อที่สาม
Even I couldn't achieve the task myself.
ข้าเองยังทำไม่ได้
There's no need for me to criticise him because of it.
เหตุใดต้องตำหนิเจ้าแปดด้วย
Can you take care of yourself?
เจ้าดูแลตัวเองให้ดีได้หรือไม่
Can you
เจ้าดูแลพี่สาวน้องสาว
take care of your siblings?
พี่ชายน้องชายของเจ้าให้ดีได้หรือไม่
Thirdly,
ข้อสาม
can you win?
เจ้าจะชนะได้หรือไม่
Tell me you can do it!
พูดถึงชนะ
If you win,
เจ้าชนะ
the Xing empire will survive.
คือต้าซิงอยู่
If you lose,
เจ้าแพ้
the Xing empire will be eradicated.
คือต้าซิงสลาย
Wang Yang,
หวังหยาง
Zheng Lu,
เจิ้งลู่
me,
ข้า
and the thousands of people
ตลอดจนคนนับพันที่ตายไป
who had died during the Morning Dew Rebellion,
ในการกบฏเจาลู่
all of us can die
เราล้วนตายได้
for the sake of your victory!
เพื่อให้เจ้ามีชัย
So, tell me.
ดังนั้นบอกข้าสิว่าเจ้า
Tell me you can do it!
ทำได้
I...
กระหม่อม
I will surely win.
ต้องชนะได้แน่
Before Xuanzong's tomb on the Golden Grain Mound now arch mature trees.
พรรณไม้โอบรอบสุสานจักรพรรดิ
The stone castle by the Qutang Gorge is surrounded by a deary field where grass rustles.
ลมสงัดพัดผ่านหุบเขาฉวีถัง
Coming to an end is a lavish banquet and a busy orchestra.
ดังเพลงโศกเร่งร้อนวนใจภิณท์พัง
As music fades, sadness takes place, over in the east the moon is up.
สุขทุกข์ขังเวียนไปใจหวาดกลัว
Even with the bow in my hand,
มือข้าง้างเกาทัณฑ์มุ่งเล็งไป
and my ambition to shoot down the sun,
เป้าหมายคือตะวันไกลสุดฟ้า
the dust stirs up
แต่อยู่ ๆ ลมกระโชกทั่วเวหา
and the sky is dark.
พสุธามืนหม่นด้วยฝุ่นธุลี
This
ไม่ยินยอม
isn't fair at all.
พร้อมใจจริง ๆ
Since when did I say
ไม่รู้ว่าเมื่อไหร่
that you can enter my room
ที่ห้องของข้า
at will?
เข้าออกได้ตามใจเสียแล้ว
Ever since Cheng Ruoyu
ตั้งแต่เฉิงรั่วอวี๋
treated this place as her second home.
กลายเป็นแขกประจำของที่นี่
Chess Overseer,
ผู้นำสำนักหมากรุก
you would be mistaken
หากท่านเห็นว่าคำพูดนี้
if you thought I was trying to provoke you.
เป็นการยั่วยุก็ผิดแล้วล่ะ
What is it then?
เช่นนั้นคืออะไร
It's a reminder.
เป็นการเตือนสติ
And,
อีกอย่าง
you need to be grateful to Qi Yan and Cheng Ruoyu
ท่านต้องขอบคุณที่ฉีเยี่ยนกับเฉิงรั่วอวี๋
for visiting Prince An tonight.
มาเยี่ยมอ๋องอันในคืนนี้
That's how you were able to avoid committing a grave mistake.
ทำให้ท่านเลี่ยงการทำผิดไปได้
This serves as a reminder to you as well.
ประโยคนี้ก็คือการเตือนสติ
I still remember
ข้ายังจำได้ว่า
the time when I first saw you.
ครั้งแรกที่พบเจ้า
You looked at me,
เจ้ามองหน้าข้า
you said my face looked familiar to you.
บอกว่าข้าหน้าตามีเมตตา
Back then, I was thinking
ตอนนั้นข้าคิดว่า
that you were
สตรีนางนี้
an annoying woman.
น่ารังเกียจจริง ๆ
After that,
ต่อมา
you were smiling
ทุกครั้งที่ข้าได้พบเจ้า
whenever I see you.
เจ้าก็ยิ้มตลอด
I was wondering
ข้าก็คิดว่า
when that wretched smile of yours
รอยยิ้มยโสน่ารังเกียจของเจ้านี้
will disappear.
เมื่อไรจะสูญสลายไปเสียที
But now,
จนกระทั่งวันนี้
not only do you not smile,
เจ้ามิเพียงไม่ยิ้ม
you always cry as well.
ยังร้องไห้เสมออีกด้วย
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
you know what?
ทรงรู้หรือไม่
In this world, you're the only person
คนเดียวบนโลกนี้ที่ทำให้หม่อมฉัน
who can make me smile and cry.
ยิ้มและร้องไห้ได้ มีแต่พระองค์
Yu'er, I'm sorry.
ขอโทษด้วย อวี๋เอ๋อร์
Sorry for making you cry so often.
ที่ทำให้เจ้าร้องไห้ตลอด
I'll stop crying.
หม่อมฉันไม่ร้องไห้
Your Majesty, as long as you stay with me,
ขอเพียงพระองค์อยู่ข้างกายหม่อมฉัน
you'll be able to see my smile
พระองค์ก็จะทรงเห็นหม่อมฉัน
forever.
แย้มยิ้มตลอดกาล
I'll stop crying.
หม่อมฉันไม่ร้องไห้
You should leave Heng'an City together with Huaizhi.
เจ้ากับหวายจื้อไปจากเหิงอัน
With him taking care of you,
มีเขาดูแลเจ้า
I won't need to worry that much about you.
ข้าก็วางใจได้บ้าง
Your Majesty, I will never leave your side.
หม่อมฉันจะไม่ไปจากพระองค์
No matter where you go,
พระองค์ทรงอยู่ที่ไหน
I'll follow.
อวี๋เอ๋อร์ก็อยู่ที่นั่น
In this lifetime,
ชีวิตนี้ข้า
I was an emperor,
เป็นประมุขของชาติ
I was the son of a eunuch,
เป็นบุตรของขันที
and I've made
ทั้งยังทำให้คน
a person like you, who love to smile,
ที่ชอบยิ้มเช่นเจ้า
cry because of me.
ต้องมาร้องไห้แบบนี้เพราะข้า
I have no regrets now.
ชีวิตนี้ก็สมบูรณ์แล้ว
I will never leave your side.
หม่อมฉันจะไม่ไปจากพระองค์
Yu'er,
อวี๋เอ๋อร์
I'm sure you will
ต่อไปเจ้า
meet someone
ต้องได้พบกับคนที่ทำให้เจ้า
who can make you smile
ยิ้มได้อย่างเดียวและ
without making you cry in the future.
พบคนที่ไม่ทำให้เจ้าร้องไห้แน่
I...
ข้า
I wish...
ข้าขอ
I wish you happiness.
ขออวยพรเจ้า
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
I'm jealous.
ข้าอิจฉา
of that person.
ข้าอิจฉาเขา
That person,
คนผู้นั้น
why can't it be me?
ทำไมจึงไม่ใช่ข้า
Why can't it be me?
ทำไมจึงเป็นข้าไม่ได้
We will always stay together.
พวกเราจะอยู่ด้วยกันไปตลอด
There's no need for you to be jealous of him.
มีอะไรน่าอิจฉาเพคะ
Your Majesty, I'm sure
คนผู้นั้น
that person is you,
ต้องเป็นฝ่าบาทแน่นอน
okay?
ตกลงหรือไม่
♪Your sudden kiss♪
♪เจ้าพลันจุมพิตมา♪
♪Finding happiness♪
♪ที่ใดขาด♪
♪Have a win-win situation♪
♪ฟ้าแลคน♪
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
you will definitely get better.
พระองค์ต้องทรงดีขึ้นแน่
In the future,
ต่อไป
I will surely smile for you.
หม่อมฉันจะยิ้มให้พระองค์ดู
♪For the fire to burn up the thoughts♪
♪จนกว่าจิตฟุ้งซ่านจะสิ้นลง♪
Sleep well.
พระองค์บรรทมสักงีบ
Everything will be fine now.
แล้วทุกอย่างก็จะดีเอง
♪Seeking ordinary words of love♪
♪ขอเพียงคู่♪
♪In the world♪
♪พูดคุยเรื่องดินฟ้า♪
♪Finding happiness♪
♪ที่ใดขาด♪
♪In both shortage and abundance♪
♪ร่วมกันเสริมเติมให้เต็ม♪
♪Have a win-win situation♪
♪ฟ้าแลคน♪
♪Want to fight and see who surrenders first♪
♪แต่ชิงดีกับฟ้า♪
Are you saying
ความหมายของท่านคือ
that the Right Chariot
โย่วเชอรู้
knew that you were going to assassinate Prince An tonight?
ว่าคืนนี้ท่านจะลงมือฆ่าอ๋องอัน
Yes.
ใช่
But, I didn't realise
แต่ข้าไม่รู้ตัวเลยว่าเขากำลัง
that he was spying on us at all.
จับตาดูอยู่
You don't need to wonder how.
ไม่ต้องดูแล้ว
I assume it was just his prediction.
เขาน่าจะแค่เดาได้
He didn't see it for himself.
ไม่ใช่เห็น
What is he up to?
เขาจะทำอะไรกันแน่
He only has one goal.
เป้าหมายของเขามีเพียงหนึ่งเดียว
He wants to stop me from assassinating Prince An.
คือยับยั้งความคิดสังหารอ๋องอันของข้า
And, he isn't doing it
อีกอย่างเขาทำเช่นนี้
for Qiu Ziliang's sake.
ไม่ใช่เพื่อฉิวจื่อเหลียง
He's doing it for another person's sake.
แต่เพื่อคนอีกผู้หนึ่ง
For whose sake?
ใคร
The Right Minister.
โย่วเซี่ยง
Sir,
ใต้เท้า
the day after tomorrow will be the appointment ceremony.
มะรืนจะเป็นวันพระราชพิธีแต่งตั้งแล้ว
Both Prince An
อ๋องอันยังมีชีวิตอยู่
and Qi Yan are still alive.
ฉีเยี่ยนก็ยังมีชีวิตอยู่
Yanzhi,
เยียนจือ
Cheng Ruoyu,
เฉิงรั่วอวี๋
Qiu Ziliang,
ฉิวจื่อเหลียง
all of them do not need to die.
ทุกคนล้วนไม่ต้องตายได้
We can begin a new game while they're still alive.
มีชีวิตอยู่เพื่อเริ่มกระดานใหม่
Have you decided to make this move?
ตัดสินใจจะขยับหมากตัวนี้แล้วหรือขอรับ
Someone.
เด็ก ๆ
Yes, sir.
- เจ้าค่ะ
Summon the divine healer here tomorrow.
พรุ่งนี้เชิญหมอเทวดามาหน่อย
His Majesty didn't assassinate Prince An last night.
เมื่อคืนฝ่าบาทไม่ได้สังหารอ๋องอัน
He just told Prince An what to do.
แต่กำชับเขาสองประโยค
He returned to the palace after that.
ก็กลับไปขอรับ
So that's the truth.
ความจริงอยู่ที่นี่
That is within my expectation.
ล้วนเป็นเรื่องที่คาดคิดไว้แล้ว
He is the same as the late emperor.
เขากับอดีตฮ่องเต้ก็เหมือนกัน
Both of them are useless fools who are soft-hearted.
ล้วนเป็นพวกสวะที่ใจอ่อน
Forget about him.
ช่างเถอะ
He is going to die soon.
คนใกล้ตาย
There's no need to hold it against him.
ก็ไม่ต้องไปถือสาเขาหรอก
By the way,
จริงสิ
what about Yanzhi?
เยียนจือเล่า
Was she up to something?
ทางนั้นมีอะไรผิดปกติหรือไม่
No.
ไม่มี
Continue to keep an eye on Yanzhi.
เจ้าเฝ้าจับตาเยียนจือไว้ให้ดีต่อไป
The appointment ceremony is tomorrow.
พระราชพิธีแต่งตั้งพรุ่งนี้
I don't want anything to go wrong.
ข้าไม่อยากให้เกิดความผิดพลาดใด ๆ
Yes, sir.
ขอรับ
What?
ทำไม
Don't you have anything to tell me?
เจ้าไม่มีอะไรพูดกับข้าหรือ
Sir, if I ask you
หากว่าข้า
to put aside every other affair
ให้ท่านละทิ้งงานทั้งหมด
and focus on meditating
ตั้งใจกักตน
so that you can neutralise the poison within your body,
ขจัดพิษก่อนค่อยออกมา
will you listen to me?
ท่านยอมหรือไม่
No.
ไม่
I shall save my breath then.
เช่นนั้นพูดไปก็ไร้ประโยชน์
But,
ทว่า
I do
ข้า
have a strong feeling.
มีความรู้สึกอย่างแรงกล้า
My Qihai meridian
ว่าช่วงนี้จุดชี่ไห่
has been twitching rapidly lately.
ปรวนแปรรุนแรงมาก
This is not the time for me to isolate myself and meditate.
ตอนนี้ไม่ใช่เวลากักตนที่ดีที่สุด
We can talk about that after Prince An has ascended the throne.
รออ๋องอันครองราชย์ก่อนค่อยว่ากันเถอะ
These are the information I can get
นี่คือข้อมูลทั้งหมดของ
regarding Nine and Lin.
อาจิ่วกับเสี่ยวหลิน
These are all that I can get
เวลากะทันหัน
within a limited amount of time.
จึงมีแค่นี้เท่านั้น
Do you really think
ท่านคิดจริง ๆ หรือว่า
they're the subordinates of the Right Minister?
พวกเขาเป็นคนของโย่วเซี่ยง
I'm just suspicious of them.
เพียงแค่สงสัย
That's why I need to find evidence.
ดังนั้นจึงต้องหาหลักฐานให้ได้
If that were the case,
หากเป็นเรื่องจริง
Right Minister
เช่นนั้นโย่วเซี่ยงผู้นี้
is an unpredictable person.
ก็ลึกล้ำเกินคาดเดาแล้ว
Have you not found Cheng Xi yet?
ยังหาเฉิงซีไม่พบหรือ
Arrange an appointment for me.
ช่วยข้าเตรียมการหน่อย
I need to see the Right Minister.
ข้าต้องการพบโย่วเซี่ยง
Understood.
ขอรับ
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
are you awake?
ทรงตื่นแล้วหรือ
How do you feel?
เป็นอย่างไรบ้าง
Do you feel much better?
ทรงรู้สึกดีขึ้นมากใช่หรือไม่เพคะ
Look at me.
ทรงดูหม่อมฉันสิ
I've fully recovered.
หายดีเหมือนเดิมแล้ว
Your Majesty, you must be shocked.
ฝ่าบาทก็ทรงแปลกใจใช่หรือไม่เพคะ
Even I didn't expect
หม่อมฉันเองก็คิดไม่ถึง
the Right Advisor to be this good at bone setting.
ว่าวิชาต่อกระดูกของโย่วซื่อจะร้ายกาจเพียงนี้
Did the Right Advisor treat your fracture for you?
โย่วซื่อต่อกระดูกให้เจ้าหรือ
And,
อีกอย่าง
Your Majesty, she was the one who gave you the medicine as well.
สมุนไพรของฝ่าบาทก็เป็นนางให้มา
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
you're worried that this may be a trap, am I right?
พระองค์ทรงกังวลว่าเป็นกับดักใช่หรือไม่
I was worried about the same thing before.
หม่อมฉันเองก็เคยกังวล
But, Your Majesty, I've tried your medicine for you.
ทว่าสมุนไพรนั้นหม่อมฉันชิมแล้ว
The medicine is fine.
กลับไม่มีปัญหาใด
Your Majesty, I'm willing
ขอเพียงทำให้ฝ่าบาทมีชีวิตอยู่
to try everything for your sake
ไม่ว่าเป็นแผนชั่วช้าอะไร
as long as you can survive.
หม่อมฉันยินดีรับมือทั้งหมด
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
instead of
เทียบกับการรอคอย
waiting for the third person to save us,
มือที่สามมาช่วยเรา
why don't we save ourselves?
มิสู้เราช่วยตัวเองดีกว่า
What do you say?
พระองค์ว่าอย่างไร
Are you sure you've fully recovered?
หายดีแล้วจริงหรือ
The appointment ceremony is tomorrow.
พรุ่งนี้คือวันพระราชพิธีแต่งตั้ง
Eunuch Qiu has sent another 50 guards
ใต้เท้าได้โยกคนจำนวนห้าสิบ
to protect Prince An.
มาคุ้มครองอ๋องอันเพิ่ม
It is said
ว่ากันว่า
that the preparation in Changming Palace
ด้านตำหนักฉางหมิง
is almost ready as well.
ก็เตรียมการไว้เกือบเสร็จแล้ว
Now, we have no choice
ทุกอย่าง
but to wait for tomorrow's arrival.
ก็รอพรุ่งนี้
What sound was that?
นั่นเสียงอะไร
It's the tune for the appointment ceremony.
มหาลำนำที่ใช้ในพระราชพิธีแต่งตั้งโดยเฉพาะ
Your Majesty, I think I heard the same tune
หม่อมฉันเคยได้ยินตอนฝ่าบาท
during your ascension ceremony.
ขึ้นครองราชย์
Tomorrow,
พรุ่งนี้
you'll be able
เจ้าก็จะได้ยินอีกครั้ง
to hear the official tune again.
อย่างเป็นทางการแล้ว
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
are you going to give up the throne?
จะทรงยอมแพ้จริงหรือ
Don't tell me you want me to fight my brother for the throne?
ไม่เช่นนั้นจะให้พี่น้องฆ่ากันเองหรือไร
Do you understand?
รู้หรือไม่
Do you regret your decision?
เสียใจหรือไม่
Are you happy?
ยินดีหรือไม่
As for me,
ข้า
I am delighted.
ยินดีมาก
Your Majesty, you...
ฝ่าบาท พระองค์
I seem different, am I right?
เปลี่ยนไปแล้วใช่หรือไม่
Your Majesty, the past you was like a bow.
ฝ่าบาทในอดีตเหมือนเกาทัณฑ์
You were always tensed up.
มักดึงจนตึงตลอดเวลา
But, the current you are...
ฝ่าบาทในตอนนี้
I was tensed up in the past
ที่เมื่อก่อนดึงจนตึง
because I couldn't bear to part with the throne.
ก็เพราะตัดใจจากบัลลังก์ไม่ได้
I always wanted the best of both worlds.
มักต้องการแผนที่งดงามทุกด้าน
But now, I'm willing to part with anything.
แต่ตอนนี้ไม่เสียดายอะไรอีก
And now,
ทว่ากลับ
I can finally win.
ชนะได้แล้ว
He doesn't want to see me?
ไม่พบ
Yes.
ใช่
The Right Minister said
โย่วเซี่ยงบอกแล้ว
that he will not see you
ว่าเพื่อเลี่ยงคำครหา
before the appointment ceremony
ก่อนพระราชพิธีแต่งตั้ง
to avoid suspicion.
จะไม่พบกับผู้นำสำนักหมากรุก
So,
ดูท่า
not only does he want to protect me,
เขามิเพียงต้องการปกป้องข้า
seems like he wants to protect Prince An as well.
ยังต้องการปกป้องอ๋องอันด้วย
Prince An?
อ๋องอัน
Stop!
หยุดนะ
Under Duke Chu's order,
ได้รับคำสั่งจากฉู่กั๋วกง
the Imperial Clothing Bureau is here
กองภูษา
to assist Prince An in choosing the right size for his attire.
มาให้ท่านอ๋องอันลองเสื้อโดยเฉพาะ
Greetings, Your Highness.
คารวะท่านอ๋องอัน
Under Duke Chu's order,
รับคำสั่งจากฉู่กั๋วกง
us from the Imperial Clothing Bureau
กองภูษา
are to assist you in choosing the right size for your attire.
มาให้ท่านอ๋องอันลองเสื้อโดยเฉพาะ
Please come in.
ทุกคนรีบเข้ามาเถอะ
We meet again,
ได้พบกันอีกแล้ว
Your Highness.
ท่านอ๋องอัน
Our future emperor.
ว่าที่ฝ่าบาท
Wait.
ไม่ใช่
I think I should address you as my nephew.
ยังคงเรียกเจ้าว่าหลานชายสักคำดีกว่า
You've laid your eyes on something you weren't supposed to.
จ้องอยากได้ของที่ไม่ควรอยากได้
Don't you think
เช่นนั้นก็ต้องจ่าย
you should pay for the consequences?
ค่าตอบแทนอะไรบ้างจริงหรือไม่
Don't kill me!
อย่าฆ่าข้า
It's you?
เป็นเจ้า
Both of you are actually ganging up on me?
คิดไม่ถึงพวกเจ้ารวมหัวกันต่อกรกับข้า
Don't blame them.
เจ้าอย่าไปโทษพวกนางเลย
Don't forget,
เจ้าอย่าลืมสิ
Right Minister was the one
ตอนนั้นเป็นโย่วเซี่ยง
who had picked these warriors of sacrifice
ที่ช่วยเจ้าเลือกนักสู้เดนตาย
for you.
กลุ่มนี้กับมือ
Heartless ingrate.
เจ้ามันคนใจคอโหดเหี้ยม
I tried my best to help you ascend the throne,
ข้าต้องการสนับสนุนเจ้าเป็นฮ่องเต้มาตลอด
but now, you're saving both Qi Yan and Qi Rong.
เจ้ากลับช่วยทั้งฉีเยี่ยนและฉีหรง
You're forsaking me instead!
แต่ไม่ช่วยข้าผู้เดียว
We're stopping you
ก็เพราะต้องการช่วยเจ้า
because we need to save you.
ดังนั้นจึงขัดขวางเจ้า
I would've succeeded a long time ago
หากไม่ใช่เขา
if you didn't stop me
ขัดขวางข้าครั้งแล้วครั้งเล่า
time and time again!
ข้าคงทำสำเร็จไปนานแล้ว
As for the rest of you,
พวกเจ้า
return to where you belong.
มาทางไหนก็กลับไปทางนั้น
How long do we have
ยังห่างจากพระราชพิธีแต่งตั้งพรุ่งนี้
before the appointment ceremony?
อีกนานเท่าไร
Less than 12 hours.
ไม่ถึงหกชั่วยามขอรับ
Let's visit Prince An.
พวกเราไปหาอ๋องอันกัน
At this hour?
ไปดึกขนาดนี้หรือขอรับ
I feel uneasy
ข้ารู้สึกตลอดว่า
for the past few days.
ใจไม่ค่อยสงบ
I need to visit him personally
เพื่อป้องกันไว้ก่อน
just in case.
ข้ายังคงไปพบเขา
I need to keep watch over him.
ด้วยตัวเองดีกว่า
Godfather.
พ่อบุญธรรม
This is great.
ยอดไปเลย
I won't need to be scared anymore once you're here.
ท่านมาแล้ว ข้าก็ไม่กลัวอีก
Why were you scared?
เจ้ากลัวอะไร
As long as I'm here,
ขอเพียงมีพ่อบุญธรรมอยู่
nobody will be able to harm you.
ใครก็ทำร้ายเจ้าไม่ได้
Understood?
เข้าใจหรือไม่
Come.
มา
Let's play with the crickets together.
พ่อบุญธรรมจะเล่นปั่นจิ้งหรีดกับเจ้า
You'll be the emperor tomorrow.
พรุ่งนี้เจ้าก็จะได้เป็นฮ่องเต้แล้ว
You should be happy.
ต้องดีใจถึงจะถูก
You must act like an emperor
เป็นฮ่องเต้
if you are one.
ก็ต้องมีท่าทางของฮ่องเต้
You must cherish my kindness
เจ้าต้องรู้จักรักถนอม
and be grateful to me.
รู้จักสำนึกบุญคุณ
(Your Highness,)
ท่านอ๋องอัน
if you wish for tomorrow's appointment ceremony
หากท่านหวังให้พระราชพิธีแต่งตั้ง
to proceed
ในวันพรุ่งนี้
smoothly,
ดำเนินไปได้อย่างราบรื่น
you mustn't tell anyone
ก็อย่าได้บอกผู้ใดว่า
that Madam Cheng was here.
วันนี้หัวหน้ากองเฉิงมา
♪We can't see clearly during the day♪
♪สิ่งที่มองไม่ชัดล้วนอยู่ยามกลางวัน♪
♪With no arguments, there are no lies♪
♪ไร้คำแก้ต่างก็ปราศจากคำลวง♪
♪But the battlefield didn't teach me to distinguish between them yet♪
♪ทว่าสนามรบไม่เคยสอนข้าให้แยกแยะ♪
♪Who says I never made a wish♪
♪ไยข้าจะไม่เคยอธิษฐาน♪
♪Who says I was once missed♪
♪ไหนเลยจะไม่เคยถูกคิดถึงเช่นกัน♪
♪Getting nightmares♪
♪ฝันร้ายเข้ามาแทรก♪
♪The vicissitudes of life where I'm wandering♪
♪ชีวิตผันผวนพเนจร♪
♪Are full of barriers without you♪
♪เมื่อไร้เจ้า อุปสรรครายล้อมกาย♪
♪And the far distance♪
♪หนทางยาวไกล♪
♪Can't let us meet in vain♪
♪ล้วนมิอาจเฉียดกายโดยเปล่า♪
♪A heavy heart doesn't go far♪
♪ยิ่งหนักอึ้งยิ่งยากลอยไกล♪
♪Even the Moon loses its glimmer♪
♪จันทร์สกาวบนฟ้า♪
♪But love prevails above all♪
♪ทำอย่างไรรักจึงยิ่งแข็งแกร่ง♪
♪Like the lost time we failed to hold on♪
♪ดีกว่าปล่อยเวลาให้สูญสิ้นไป♪
Good.
ดี
Godfather.
พ่อบุญธรรม
Very good.
ดีมาก
You look great.
เจ้าดีมาก
You're the new emperor of the Xing empire.
เจ้าเป็นประมุขคนใหม่ของต้าซิง
You're the hope of the Xing empire!
เป็นความหวังของต้าซิง
Good!
ดี
Come.
มา
I'm in a great mood today.
ข้าดีใจ
I'll put on your hat for you.
จะสวมให้เจ้ากับมือตัวเอง
Come.
มา
What do you think?
เป็นอย่างไรบ้าง
Godfather,
พ่อบุญธรรม
will Brother attend today's appointment ceremony?
วันนี้เสด็จพี่จะเสด็จมาร่วมงานหรือไม่
Do you wish for him to attend it?
เจ้าอยากให้เขามาหรือไม่
I do.
อยาก
You are the new emperor.
เจ้าเป็นประมุขคนใหม่
You get to make the call here.
เจ้าว่าอย่างไรก็อย่างนั้น
Someone!
เด็ก ๆ
Yes, sir.
ขอรับ
Invite Qi Yan
ไปเชิญฉีเยี่ยน
and ask him to attend the appointment ceremony.
ให้เขามาคอยชื่นชมพระราชพิธี
Let him observe the ceremony
อยู่ด้านข้าง
as I crown the new emperor.
ข้าจะสวมมงกุฎให้เจ้าชีวิตคนใหม่
Yes, sir.
ขอรับ
Are you happy now?
พอใจแล้วกระมัง
By the way, Godfather,
จริงสิ พ่อบุญธรรม
the imperial crown seems pretty heavy.
มงกุฎนี้เหมือนหนักยิ่ง
Heavy?
หนัก
Of course. You have to shoulder the fate of the entire Xing empire.
นี่คือความรับผิดชอบต่อต้าซิง
There's no need to be afraid.
เจ้ากลัวอะไร
As long as I'm around,
ขอเพียงมีข้าอยู่
you'll be able to withstand the burden!
เจ้าก็รับไหว
Godfather.
พ่อบุญธรรม พ่อบุญธรรม
This...
นี่ นี่
♪Life is a dream, how long do happy times last♪
♪ชีวิตล่องลอยดุจฝัน เคยสุขกี่ครั้ง♪
♪The sword can't break this karma♪
♪ชักดาบฟันฟาด กลับมิอาจสะบั้นเหตุและผล♪
♪Look how blurry and lonely the world is♪
♪มองฟ้ามองดินล้วนไม่ยินไม่แยแส♪
♪Still can't let go of this life as time goes by♪
♪ตะวันรุ่งจันทราโรย ชีพนี้ยังคงน่าถนอม♪
♪Even the iron and golden dagger-axe cannot extinguish the fire in my heart♪
♪ควบอาชาพร้อมอาวุธ มิอาจหยุดไฟในทรวง♪
♪Remembering the past and letting time while away♪
♪คิดถึงฝันในวันเก่า นานเท่านาน ยังคงเจ็บ♪
♪The past is in front of you♪
♪อดีตพลันไหลผ่านสองตา♪
♪Forgetting while piecing it together♪
♪ทางหนึ่งเพียรลืม อีกทางเพียรจำ♪
♪Like when I sincerely put my hands together♪
♪หากข้าประกบมือประนมกร♪
♪I only wish that you can be saved♪
♪ไหว้วอนให้เจ้าได้หลุดพ้น♪
♪The past is in front of you♪
♪อดีตพลันไหลผ่านสองตา♪
♪Forgetting while piecing it together♪
♪ทางหนึ่งเพียรลืม อีกทางเพียรจำ♪
♪Like when I sincerely put my hands together♪
♪หากข้าประกบมือประนมกร♪
♪I only wish that you can be saved♪
♪ไหว้วอนให้เจ้าได้หลุดพ้น♪